Continuing Education Records 1947-1980
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Continuing Education Records
1947-1980
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Archives 241
2 linear feet 3 containers
Includes correspondence, reports, research & publications, brochures, meeting notes, personnel files. Also includes scrapbook pages related to WSU/WSC program in Spokane, the Spokane Art Center and continuing education at various Washington cities and Portland, Oregon.
Organizational History:
Continuing education has been defined variously. As a specific effort, aside from content, continuing education takes the form of off-campus classes, correspondence course, recorded instructional materials, special short courses or workshops, and so on. In one form or another Washington State University has been involved in continuing education since its inception. Early efforts were chiefly concerned with agriculture. The nature of these programs changed considerably after the establishment of the Agr icultural Extension Service in 1915. In later years an engineering extension program was added, along with general extension, the last dating from 1921. General Extension's effort mostly nearly resembled continuing education as commonly defined.
In the late 1940s, the State College initiated various efforts at off-campus classes, taught chiefly at night. These "branches" were informally known as "Little WSCs." The program at Spokane was the most extensive. It survived in limited form following fiscal cutbacks in 1951 that basically cancelled the larger effort, with a program of night classes that lasted until 1968.
In the years following 1970, distance classes, video-tape instruction and similar programs led to the re-establishment of off-campus classes in various cities around Washington, and even one in an out-of-state location. These classes all involved spe cial subjects, mainly technical, and often were presented at the request of employers. In the years 1977-80, these programs became involved in complex state wide educational planning effort and in so-called "turf wars" that arose as schools with low enrollment sought to deploy their excess faculty members in extended campus programs.
The records of the Office of Continuing Education consist of correspondence, reports, project research and implementation, publications, brochures and pamphlets, meeting notes, and personnel files. The earlier records come from disassembled scrapbook s, and scrapbook material that had not been mounted. Records from the years after 1970 are from the files of John Cronland, Director of Continuing Education.
The Collection is open for research use.
Records of the Continuing Education Office were transferred to the Washington State University Libraries in 1989 (Accession Number UA89-03).
Cronland, John, Director of Continuing Education
Washington State University. Office of Continuing Education--Archives; Washington State University. Continuing Education Office.; State College of Washington. Continuing Education Office.; Washington State University. Office of Continuing Education--Records and correspondence; Spokane Art Center--History--Archives
Pullman (Wash.)--Study and teaching (Continuing education)--Archives; Tri-Cities (Wash.)--Study and teaching (Continuing education)--Archives; Washington (State)--Study and teaching (Continuing education)--Archives
Continuing education--Washington (State)--Records and correspondence
Washington (State); Colleges and Universities; Scrapbooks; Photographs
- Oversize. Scrapbook pages; Newspaper clippings and photos Chiefly related to WSC/WSU program in Spokane, including Little WSC, the Spokane Art Center, nursing education, and night classes, 1953-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
- Scrapbook pages with newspaper clippings and photos, relative to the Little WSC program and the Spokane Art Center, 1947-1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Scrapbook pages of newspaper clippings, photos, brochures, all relative to program at Spokane, including the Spokane Art Center, night classes, development of nursing education program, a proposed graduate study center and the acquisi tion of the former Public Library, 1961-1969 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
- Correspondence and enclosures regarding use of television and videotape for education; matters at Richland, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- General correspondence regarding classes at Wenatchee and Walla Walla; also professional organizations for those working in continuing education, 1974-1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence and enclosures regarding activities at the Tri Cities; also matters of statewide planning by Council on Post-Secondary Education (CPE), 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence regarding activities of several univer- sities at Tri Cities, demand for classes at Tri Cities, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- General correspondence regarding programs at Tri Cities, 1975-1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Correspondence regarding videotape continuing education courses, statewide planning, the role of community colleges, and the use of telecommunication facilities, 1974-1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Correspondence and related materials regarding offering of graduate degrees through the Continuing Education, video engineering classes in Portland, OR. and the Oregon educational planning office, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 15)